Today you have come here to worship me as Shri Ganesha.
今天你們來到這裡，以錫呂．伽涅沙的形式崇拜我
We have been singing the praise of Shri Ganesha before every puja.
在每個普祭之前，我們都會唱頌 崇拜錫呂．伽涅沙的歌曲
And we have such tremendous respect for Shri Ganesh
我們對錫呂．伽涅沙有著如此高的尊敬
because we have found out that unless and until Shri Ganesha,
因為我們發現除非錫呂．伽涅沙
who is the symbol of our innocence, is not awakened within us,
他是我們內在純真象徵。他若未在我們體內被喚醒
we cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.
我們無法進入神的國度
And even to stay there and to enjoy the blessings of Shri Ganesha,
即使只是待在那裡，享受錫呂．伽涅沙的祝福
we have to have our innocence fully blossoming.
我們必須要使我們的純真之花完全地盛開
So we praise Him and He is very easily praised.
所以我們崇拜他，而他是非常容易被崇拜的
And whatever we might have done wrong before coming to Sahaja Yoga,
而無論來到霎哈嘉瑜伽之前，我們曾做錯過什麼事
He completely forgives
他都完全原諒
because He is the eternal child.
因為他是永恆的孩子
You have seen children,
你曾看過孩子們
when you slap them, sometimes get angry with them,
當你摑他巴掌，有時對他們發怒
they forget it. They only remember the love
他們忘記了，他們只會記得那份愛
and not what they have suffered at your hands.
而不是他們曾在你手下受了多少苦
Till they grow up, they do not have memory of bad things done to them.
直到他們長大，他們沒有任何不好的記憶
From the very beginning,
從最一開始
a child is born to a mother,
一個孩子來到母親肚子裡
he doesn’t know what he has gone through.
他不知道他經歷了什麼
Then gradually the memory starts working
慢慢地記憶開始運作
and he starts restoring things within himself.
他開始在內在拼湊事情
But in the beginning, only he remembers what nice things have happened to him.
但在一開始，他只記得發生在他身上美好的事情
So we always like to ponder about our childhood,
所以我們總是喜歡憶起我們的童年
what we enjoyed in our childhood.
那些我們享受的童年時光
But as we start growing up, we start remembering all the miseries
但當我們漸漸長大，我們開始記得所有悲慘的事
and all the tribulations we had to go through.
所有我們必須經歷的苦難
All the ordeals, through which we have passed, we try to magnify it.
所有的嚴峻考驗。即使我們已經走過了， 我們仍嘗試放大來看
In childhood, the children only remember the people who have loved them
小時候，孩童只會記得那些愛著他們的人
and not the people who have hurt them. They don’t want to remember perhaps.
而不是那些傷害他們的人，或許他們不願意記得
It looks like that. But when they grow up,
看似如此，但當他們長大
they only try to remember those people who have harmed them or have troubled them
他們只記得那些傷害或困擾他們的人
and that’s how they make themselves very miserable.
他們就是這樣，令自己變得非常悲慘
But the principle of Ganesha is extremely subtle, is the subtlest of subtle.
但伽涅沙的原理是極度精微的，精微之中的精微
And it exists in everything, that it exists in the matter, in the form of vibrations.
且祂存在於所有事物中， 祂以能量的形式存在於物質中
There is no matter, which is without vibrations.
沒有任何物質是沒有能量的
It has vibrations, which are seen even in the atoms
物質有能量，甚至原子中也能看見能量
and also in the molecules of all matter that is existing.
在所有物質中的分子上也有能量
So Shri Ganesha is the first one who was established in the matter, as well.
所以錫呂．伽涅沙也是第一位被建立在物質之內的
As a result, we can see, He exists in the sun,
因此，我們可以看到祂存在於太陽之內
He exists in the moon, He exists in the whole universe,
祂存在於月亮之內， 祂存在於整個宇宙之中
in the whole creation, and He continues to exist in human beings also.
祂存在於所有創造之中， 祂也繼續存在在人類之中
Only the human beings have capacity
只有人類有這個能力
to somehow or other cover up your – the innocence.
以某種方式去掩蓋你的純真
Otherwise, animals are innocent.
否則，動物是純真的
Human beings have the freedom; if they want, they can cover up
人類擁有這種自由，如果他們想要，他們可以掩蓋
their innocence, they can shut down the doors of Shri Ganesha
他們的純真。他們可以關上錫呂．伽涅沙的門
and say that He does not exist. They can cloud it.
並且說，祂並不存在，他們可以遮蓋它
And that is why we find among human beings,
那就是為什麼我們發現人類
that they are doing so many horrible things,
他們做了這麼多可怕的事
avoiding the existence of Shri Ganesh.
否定了錫呂．伽涅沙的存在
But He acts. He acts in a way
但祂會行動
that He shows natural results of our wrongdoings.
祂會揭露我們所做的錯事應有的後果
Like if you do things, which are not pleasing to Shri Ganesh,
好比如果你做了使錫呂．伽涅沙不開心的事情
He goes up to a point, forgives you up to a point,
祂等待到一個階段，原諒你到一個地步
and then He starts emerging out as diseases, as physical diseases,
接著祂開始以疾病，身體疾病的形式顯露出來
and in women, it becomes a mental disease.
在女人之中，成為心理疾病
Also, it can create problems in the nature.
這也在自然生態中形成問題
The natural catastrophes are, also,
自然災難也只是
only the curse of Shri Ganesha.
錫呂．伽涅沙的詛咒罷了
When people start doing wrong things,
當人們開始做錯誤的事
behaving in a wrong manner, collectively,
整體行為表現都是錯誤的
then the natural catastrophes come to teach them a lesson.
那自然災難便會到來，給他們一個教訓
So in His essence, though He exists in everything,
所以在祂的本質上，雖然祂存在於所有事物之中
also in that, He has capacity to assert His will,
在那之中，祂也有能力去維護祂的意志
to bring forth the destruction of the whole world.
帶出毀滅世界的力量
We have Shri Ganesha’s idea as a minute thing.
我們將錫呂．伽涅沙想得極其微小
We think, He can go on a little mouse, so He must be very minute.
我們想著，祂可以坐在小老鼠上， 那他一定非常微小
He is as minute as He is great.
祂是同等微小，也是同等偉大的
He surpasses all the Deities because of His wisdom.
祂因祂的智慧，超越所有的神祇
He is the giver of wisdom. He gives us wisdom. He makes us learn.
祂是智慧的賜予者，祂賜給我們智慧， 祂使我們學習
He is our Guru, in that respect, Mahaguru,
祂是我們的導師，尊敬地說是，偉大的導師
because He teaches us how we should behave.
因為祂教導我們的行為舉止
If you try to surpass Him and try to misbehave,
如果你試著越過祂，試著踰矩
even the Mother won’t support you,
甚至連母親都不會支持你
because She knows, that those who surpass Shri Ganesha
因為她知道那些越過了錫呂．伽涅沙的人
are also the people who will never respect the Mother.
也是永遠不會尊重母親的人
So He is the epitome of respect for Mother. Epitome.
所以他是尊重母親的象徵、典範
He does not know any other gods. He does not know Sadashiva.
祂並不知道其他任何的神，祂不知道至高濕婆神
He doesn’t know anybody else, but He only respects the Mother.
祂不知道其他任何人，祂只知道尊敬母親
So He is the one who is the power of devotion and complete surrender to Mother,
所以祂是奉獻與完全交託於母親的力量
and that’s why He is the most powerful Deity among all the Deities
那就是為什麼，在眾多神祇之中祂是最有力量的
and nobody can surpass Him in His powers.
在祂的力量下，沒有任何人可以超越祂
We have to understand that as children are growing,
我們必須要了解，當孩子長大
Shri Ganesha starts growing in them also,
錫呂．伽涅沙也開始在他們之中成長
but as they are human beings they can, somehow or other, try
但因為他們是人類，他們可以以某種方式試著
to overpower Shri Ganesha. So is the duty of parents who are sahaja yogis to see
去跨越錫呂．伽涅沙。 所以這是作為霎哈嘉瑜伽士的父母的職責去觀看
that they look after their children in a way, in a detached way,
去照顧他們的孩子，以一個不依戀的方式
to see that Shri Ganesha in them is settled.
去觀看錫呂．伽涅沙在他們之中安頓下來
The first sign of Shri Ganesha in a child is wisdom.
在孩子中，錫呂．伽涅沙的第一個跡象就是智慧
If the child is not wise, if he is troublesome,
如果孩子沒有智慧，如果他很令人煩惱
if he does not know how to behave, then that shows that the Shri Ganesha
如果他行為表現不佳，那代表錫呂．伽涅沙
is being attacked by him.
正在被他攻擊
And these days in the modern times, as it is, children are very much under attack.
在現在這個摩登時代，孩子經常遭受侵襲
Innocence is under attack.
純真被侵害
And it is very difficult for people to make a fine line
人們要找出孩子可以觸碰與不能觸碰的
as to how far to go with children and how far not to go.
合適的界線是非常困難的
Today’s lecture would be more concerning about how far to go with Shri Ganesha
今天的課題會更關注於，錫呂．伽涅沙觸及到的地方
as far as children are concerned because that’s a very important point.
就孩童而言，因為那是非常重要的
Because He is the giver of wisdom. So the parents must understand
因為他是智慧的賜予者。所以父母必須明白
that, “If He is the giver of wisdom, there should be wisdom, wisdom within me.
如果他是智慧的賜予者，那在我之中應也有智慧
And if I have the wisdom, then I have the balance,
如果我有智慧，那我應處於平衡之中
and I don’t lose tempers with children,
我不會對孩子發怒
but I try to correct them, but in such a manner that they get corrected.”
我會試著糾正他們， 但以一種方式，使他們得以被糾正
On the contrary, if you try to be very harsh with your children,
相反地，如果你試著對你的孩子非常嚴厲
they might react and they might go astray.
他們有可能反彈，他們有可能會走偏
Or you try to restrict them too much,
或你太過約束他們
then also they will behave in the same manner.
那他們也會有一樣的表現
So one thing is to be taught to your own children,
所以，你要教你的孩子一件事
as Shri Ganesha Himself does, that “respect your Mother.”
如同錫呂．伽涅沙本身也是如此， 要尊重你的母親
Your Mother means your Holy Mother and your own mother.
你的母親是指， 你的神聖母親以及你自身的母親
That is very important. If the father doesn’t make the child respect the mother,
那是非常重要的， 如果父親不教導孩子尊重母親
the child can never be all right.
那孩子永遠無法妥當
Because the authority comes from the father no doubt, but mother must be respected.
因為雖然父親有權力沒錯， 但母親必須被尊重
But for that, it is very important that mother must respect the father.
但為此，非常重要的是， 母親必須要尊重父親
So in the presence of children, if you start fighting with each other,
所以在孩子面前，如果你們開始爭吵
misbehaving, and talking in a manner that is not proper,
行為不端，以不適當的方式說話
also will have a very bad effect on the Ganesha Tattwa of the child.
同樣會嚴重損害孩子的伽涅沙原理
This upbringing is a very important thing in Sahaja Yoga
養育孩子在霎哈嘉瑜伽之中是非常重要的
because by God’s grace you all have got realised children.
因為神的恩惠，你們都獲得了自覺的靈
So you must know how far to go with your children
所以你必須知道，你的孩子的界線在哪裡
to make them wiser, to be moral, to be righteous.
使他們更聰明、有道德、有正義感
First thing is that you should try to preserve their wisdom.
首先你應該試著去保護他們的智慧
If they say something wise, you must appreciate.
如果他們說了有智慧的話，你要表達讚賞
But they should not also say out of place, out of grace.
但他們也不應該為了地位，為了被欣賞而說
So the misbehaviour is also not to be tolerated, in the sense,
所以行為不端也不應該被容忍，也就是說
that whatever is wisdom within, has to be expressed outside as light.
在他內在的智慧，必須要如同光一樣，表現在外在
Now we go further with it to see how far Shri Ganesha acts.
現在我們再深入地看錫呂．伽涅沙遍及多遠
As I said, in the subtlest of subtlest He exists, but you have to awaken Him.
如同我說的，祂存在於最精微的精微之中， 但你必須要喚醒祂
For example, you have seen the water, which is vibrated – means what?
舉例來說，你也見過能量水， 意思是什麼
Vibrated means the Ganesha Tattwa is been enlightened in that water.
有能量意思是，伽涅沙原理在那水之中被啟發了
So when that water goes into your stomach, or into your eyes,
所以當那水進入你的胃，或是你的眼睛
or wherever you want to put it, it acts; acts in a way
或任何你想要放的地方，它起作用
that it excites the Shri Ganesha Tattwa into anything that you put it.
它在任何你放水的地方，激活伽涅沙原理
Now you have seen, we have got miracles of agriculture, to begin with.
現在，你看過，首先我們有農業的奇蹟
Miracles of agriculture is such that people are amazed,
農業的奇蹟令人們驚奇
but it’s very simple. Once you start exciting the Ganesh Principle
但這是非常簡單的，一旦你開始在種子中激活
into the seed, it becomes ten times, sometimes hundred times.
伽涅沙原理，它變成十倍、有時百倍
Even the Mother Earth, which we think to be something dead,
甚至大地母親，我們認為她是沒有生命的
can be vibrated.
也能被賦予能量
Supposing, you sahaja yogis walk bare feet on the ground,
假設，你們霎哈嘉瑜伽士，在大地上赤腳走路
the Mother Earth gets vibrated.
大地母親能獲得能量
Such Mother Earth will act on the trees, on the grass, on the flowers, on everything.
這樣的大地母親會在樹上、草地上、花朵上， 一切事物上作用
As it is, the sahaja yogis have been telling me that in their ashrams
如同，霎哈嘉瑜伽士不斷告訴我的，在他們的靈舍
all the flowers that grow, are out of size and very fragrant.
所有的花朵都長得特別大，而且非常芳香
Like daisies never had fragrance in London or in England, never.
像雛菊在倫敦，或在整個英國都從未有香味、從未
Now, the daisy size was so small; it has become so big,
雛菊原本的大小是這麼的小，現在變得這麼大
and you see them everywhere, so fragrant. And it is a miracle; the first time
你到處都能看到雛菊，這麼地芳香， 這是一個奇蹟
when I told somebody that the daisies are fragrant, they couldn’t believe it.
當我第一次告訴別人，雛菊有香味， 他們無法相信
And when they saw the fragrance; they were surprised.
當他們看到、聞到那股香味，他們非常驚訝
In the same way, Ganesha Tattwa understands, thinks, organises, works out
以這樣的方式，伽涅沙原理理解、思考、組織、成就
if it is awakened. If it is not, it is sleeping, then it does not.
當祂是清醒的。如果祂在沉睡，那就不會
So it acts, it works out.
所以祂作用、祂成就
Like a little seed when it sprouts, at the tip of the seed,
就像一個小小的種子，當它發芽，在種子的頂端
there is a little cell, which has got the Ganesh Tattwa, which is been awakened.
有一個小小的天花板，其擁有被喚醒了的伽涅沙原理
So it knows how to go down, how to go around a stone,
所以它知道要如何往下延伸、如何繞過石頭
and how to embed itself, and how to reach the source of water.
如何栽種自己、如何接觸到水源
But it has only the sense how far to go to exist, how far to go to nourish yourself,
但它只知道，要如何存活下去、要如何滋養自己
on a very material plane, how to allow the tree to grow.
在物質的世界，要如何使樹木成長茁壯
But this Ganesh Tattwa starts becoming very, very subtle and subtlest
但此伽涅沙原理，在額輪的位置開始
at the point of Agnya chakra.
變得非常精微、極其精微
At the time of Agnya chakra, it understands
在額輪時，祂明白
that it has now the spiritual dimension.
現在已經到了靈性的維度
The same Ganesha Tattwa, which acted in a small little tip of a root,
那在植物根部的小小尖端作用的， 同樣的伽涅沙原理
now acts for the spiritual thing.
現在也在靈性上作用
That’s why people close their eyes when they meditate –
那就是為什麼當人們靜坐時會閉上眼睛
because they don’t want to see anything else, but they want Shri Ganesha just
因為他們不想看見任何其他東西，他們只想要
to act for the meditative process of their Kundalini.
當他們靜坐時， 錫呂．伽涅沙能作用於他們的昆達里尼之上
This process of meditation, when we close our eyes, acts,
靜坐的過程中，當我們閉上我們的雙眼，祂行動
but if you see, if somebody is sleeping and he is dreaming,
但當你看到， 假設一個人睡著了而他正在作夢
you will see, there will be, the eyes will be all the time moving,
你會看到，他的眼睛會一直移動
they will be moving eyes.
他們的眼睛會一直移動
This Ganesh Tattwa is now acted by your attention.
這個伽涅沙原理現在作用於你的注意力上
If you have an attention, which is all the time going from this place to that place,
如果你的注意力，總是在這裡、那裡
to that place, to that place, then it is affected,
飄移不定，那祂是受到影響的
specially in the case when we start looking at men, looking at women, all the time.
特別是當我們開始 一直看男人、看女人
Then the – also our Ganesha Tattwa gets very much destroyed.
那我們的伽涅沙原理會嚴重地受損
Such people are difficult for rising in their ascent
這樣的人要靈性升進是非常困難的
because Agnya itself goes out.
因為額輪本身出走了
Then this Ganesha Tattwa can also be reduced if you are very materialistic,
接著，當你太過物質主義， 這個伽涅沙原理也會被削弱
always worried about your things... like
總是擔心你的事物，像是…
you have something in the house you are worried about, and looking at everything,
你擔心家裡的某個東西，你盯著所有事物
all the time trying to correct it and all the time worried about the matter.
總是試圖修正它，無時無刻擔心物質
Then also, this Ganesha Tattwa can be lost
那這個伽涅沙原理也會喪失
because you are all the time worried about these things.
因為你總是擔心這些事情
Like we are going to the shop and we are seeing everything,
像我們去一間店，我們看著每件事物
“What is there? What is there? What should I buy? What should I buy?”
那是什麼？那是什麼？我該買什麼？我該買什麼？
Like that also if you do too much, it will be.
如果你太過那麼做，也會
But supposing you are buying something out of beauty, for beauty.
但假設你因為美麗而買了某件東西，因為美麗
You want to buy something for beautifying your house.
你想要買某個東西來裝點你的家
That means, you are trying to do something to please others.
代表你試著做些事情，來使別人感到愉快
You are doing it to make others very happy.
你為了使別人開心而這麼做
Then, it acts the other way round, then it increases your ascent.
那這是相反的，這會增進你的靈性升進
But if it is done only to create a kind of a joy for others,
但只有在為了他人的喜悅而做時
sharing of the beauty of whatever you have bought or you have taken.
無論你買了什麼、拿了什麼，分享它的美麗
But supposing, you are buying anything for making others feel jealous –
但假設你是為了使別人感到忌妒而買
that also I’ve recently learned, that there is a capacity like that for people
那也是，我最近才知道，人們有可能這麼做
to buy something to make others jealous, not to make somebody feel happy.
為了讓他人感到忌妒而買，而不是讓他們感到快樂
If there are people who buy things just to make others feel jealous,
如果有人只是為了讓人感到忌妒而買東西
then also their Ganesha Tattwa can be destroyed.
那他們的伽涅沙原理也會被摧毀
What you should buy? Anything, you should make a beautiful house.
你應該買什麼，你應該要打造一個漂亮的家
When somebody comes to your house,
當人們來到你家
you should say, “Oh, what a nice thing we have seen.”
你應該說：「喔這是多麼美麗啊！」
Not attachment to the thing, but attachment to the thing how people feel,
不依戀於那個物件，但依戀於人們的感受
how they feel nice and relaxed, and
他們感到如何喜悅與放鬆
they feel their Shri Ganesha within them, which is beauty.
他們可以感到錫呂．伽涅沙在他們之中，那是美麗
When this feeling comes in, then we should say there is Ganesh Tattwa.
當這股感受到來，那我們可以說那有伽涅沙原理
And is a very motherly feeling it is. Like a mother always wants to give
這是一個如同慈母般的感受，像一個母親總是想要給予
sweet things to her children, beautiful things to her children.
她的孩子甜美的事物、美麗的事物
In the same way, in that you have that vatsalya, as is called,
同樣地，在那之中你有那被稱作vatsalya
is the feeling of the mother for the child. That subtle feeling you have that,
是一個母親對孩子的感受，你擁有的那精微的感受
“People have come to my house. Now see how they are happy,
「人們來到我的房子，看看他們現在有多快樂
they are enjoying this and they are appreciating it.”
他們很享受而且對此欣賞。」
In that way, you also satisfy a very great Ganesha Principle,
那樣，你也滿足了非常偉大的伽涅沙原理
is that you have taken note of the artists.
因你也形同於獲取了藝術家的成果
Though the artists are creating their all beautiful things out of matter
雖然那些美麗的事物，是藝術家從物質製成的
through the Swadisthana, but without Swadisthana being governed
透過腹輪，但如果沒有錫呂．伽涅沙支配的根輪
by Shri Ganesha, it cannot be beautiful.
是不會美麗的
These days, as you see, the artists are taking to all sorts
這些日子 如你所見 這些藝術家都在製造一些
of grotesque things and very immoral things.
怪誕和非常不道德的事物
And these things are of no eternal value.
這些事情都沒有任何永恆的價值
Today people will buy them and tomorrow they will throw away.
今天人們會買，明天他們就會將之丟棄
Only the things, which have got the subtle Ganesh Principle in it acting,
只有那些內在有精微伽涅沙原理的事物
which makes you soothe down, which makes you feel peaceful,
能安撫你、使你感到平靜
which makes you feel happy, is the one that is appreciated.
使你感到快樂，那才是值得欣賞的
So Shri Ganesha establishes within you the higher Self.
所以錫呂．伽涅沙安頓於你的內在。祂是高我
So the baser self, which enjoys all baser things of lives,
所以低等的我，享受那些生命中低等的事物
are being curtailed down,
被縮減
being cut down, sometimes completely destroyed by Shri Ganesha.
被壓縮，有時會完全地被錫呂．伽涅沙所摧毀
I’ll give you an example of Mona Lisa. If you see Mona Lisa –
我舉個例子，如果你看蒙娜麗莎
I mean I don’t know, she cannot be an actress,
我是說我不知道，她不可能是一名演員
she cannot win any beauty contest, I think.
她不可能贏得任何一個選美大會，我認為
She… her face is very serene, very motherly, very pure, her eyes.
她… 她的臉非常安詳，像一名母親。她的眼睛非常純潔
And why is it that she’s eternally so much appreciated?
為什麼她可以恆久地被欣賞？
The reason is, there is Ganesha Principle in her. She’s a mother.
原因是，她內在有伽涅沙原理。她是一個母親
And the story about that one is that this lady had lost her child
這個故事是，這個婦人失去了她的孩子
and she would never smile, she would never cry.
她永不會笑 ，也永不會哭泣
And one little child was brought to her, and when she saw the child,
一個小孩被帶到她面前，當她看到那個小孩
then the smile that came on her face of that love for the child,
因為對那孩子的愛，微笑漸漸爬上她的臉龐
is been depicted by this great artist.
這樣的微笑，被這個偉大的藝術家描繪出來
And that’s why people are appreciating it. And you have seen in the West,
那就是為什麼人們如此欣賞她。你可以看到在西方
though the people don’t show much interest in the mother-child relationships,
即使人們並不這麼關心母親與孩子的關係
anywhere you go, is the mother and child theme is the best.
無論你去到任何地方，母親與孩子的主題都是最佳的
They’ll show you a photograph, “This is mother and child,
他們會給你看一幅繪畫：「這是母親與孩子
this is Christ’s Mother and Child.
這是耶穌的母親與孩子
When the Christ was brought down, the Mother is there,”
當基督被帶到世間，母親在這裡。」
They have to have Mother and the Child Principle acting,
他們一定要有母親與孩子的原理運行
otherwise, that picture is not regarded as something great.
否則，那幅繪畫就無法被稱作是偉大的
Or you have to have, actually, Christ who is a Ganesha Principle Himself to be shown.
或者你必須要顯現基督，事實上基督本身就是伽涅沙原理
I haven’t seen any picture as such of those days
我還沒有看過任何那個時代的繪畫
where these principles are not there. Even Picasso has used it.
沒有這些原理在內的，甚至畢卡索也有使用
Even people who have been quite modern, had to use this principle
甚至連非常當代的人也都有使用這些原理
to popularise. But some people have used to popularise,
去推廣。但有些人用來推廣的
not the Ganesh Principle, just anti-Ganesh principles.
不是伽涅沙原理，而是反伽涅沙原理
All such things have vanished into thin air, and I see now, gradually,
所有這些都會消失在空氣中，我看到現在慢慢地
it’s all going down and down and down and down.
都在不斷不斷地向下沉淪
Despite the fact, people have lost their morals, but still,
儘管事實是，人們已經失去了他們的倫理，但是
they would like to have Rembrandt, they’d like to have Leonardo da Vinci,
他們還是喜歡林布蘭跟李奧納多．達文西
they would like to have such artists, who have done Mother and Child.
他們會喜歡這些描繪了母親與孩子的藝術家
Is very surprising. Even I went to Austria this time, I said,
這非常令人驚訝。甚至我這次去奧地利，我說：
“What statues you have?” Said, “We have got beautiful Madonna and the Child.”
「你們有怎樣的雕像？」 他們說：「喔我們有很漂亮的聖母瑪麗亞與孩子。」
So this principle is the most pleasing principle.
所以這個原理是最令人喜悅的原理
Is the most pleasing principle for human beings
對人們來說，是最令人喜悅的原理
to see the children, to play with them, to enjoy their company.
去看孩子們，與他們遊玩，享受他們的陪伴
Why? Because it has that sweetness of a child.
為什麼？因為孩子是那樣的甜美
It’s really, I should say, tickles joy within you when you see a child.
當你看到一個孩子，這是真的， 我應該說，發自內心的喜悅
Immediately the face becomes different.
你的臉馬上就變得不同
I have told you that I’ve seen even a crocodile cracking her eggs.
我告訴你，我曾經看過一隻鱷魚壓裂她的蛋
I mean, they showed it in a film,
我是說，他們在電影上播放
and you should have seen the eyes of the crocodile at that time,
你應該要看看，那時候那隻鱷魚的眼神
how carefully she was cracking. So beautiful her eyes were,
她有多麼小心翼翼地壓，她的眼神是如此美麗
full of – such love pouring out of her eyes.
她的眼睛充滿著愛
And you can’t believe, these are the eyes of the same crocodile.
你無法相信，這是同一隻鱷魚的眼睛
And so slowly she’s cracking with her mouth all the eggs
她慢慢地用她的嘴巴壓碎蛋殼
and the little, little crocodiles coming out. And then she brings them on the shore
小小鱷魚爬出來，接著她帶他們到岸邊
and washes them in the mouth all the time,
不停地用嘴巴將他們洗乾淨
so carefully, like a bathroom, she uses her mouth, you see.
如此小心，像淋浴間一樣的，使用她的嘴巴，你看
You should see how animals also act to their children.
你應該要看看，動物都如何對待他們的孩子
But when you become sort of modern, so-called,
但當你變得，我們說，現代化之後
your actions are very funny. There are people who are killing children,
你的行為會非常可笑，還有人在謀殺孩子
there are people who are abusing children. I mean, it is worse than rakshasas.
有人在虐待孩童。我是說，這簡直比羅剎魔還惡劣
Even rakshasas have not done, pishakshas have not done. The Ganas are surprised –
甚至羅剎魔(rakshasas)都沒有這樣做過， 畢舍遮(pishachas)也沒有這樣做過， 伽藍仙眾都感到驚訝
“What sort of these new creatures have come up from where,
這個新怪物是從那裡冒出來的？
that they have no love for their children, that they can kill their children,
他們對他們的孩子毫無關愛， 他們可以殺害自己的孩子
murder them, break their hands. These are their own children.
謀殺他們、折斷手臂，這是他們自己的孩子
If they do this to their own children, what will they do to other’s children?”
如果他們都這樣對自己的孩子， 那他們會怎樣對待別人的孩子？
So love for your child has to be absolutely important,
愛你的孩子，是非常重要的
but you should not as sahaja yogis
但你作為霎哈嘉瑜伽士，你不應該
have only attachment for your child, first thing.
只依戀你的孩子，這是第一
And the second thing is, you must know how to give
第二是，你必須要知道要如何
a complete margin to your love. The margin is benevolence:
為你的愛留一點餘裕， 這樣的餘裕是有利於孩子的
“Is it benevolent for my child? Am I spoiling my child?
這對我的孩子是好的嗎？ 我是否過於溺愛我的孩子了呢？
Am I too much encouraging my child? Am I playing into the hands of my child?
我是否太過鼓勵孩子了？ 我是否被孩子主導了？
Or I am managing the child alright?”
或我能妥善地管教孩子？
Because in childhood, the father and mother have to manage the children.
因為在童年時，父母必須要管教孩子
They have to tell children and children have to be obedient
他們必須要教導孩子，孩子必須要服從
and they have to listen to parents. But these days children are not obedient.
他們必須要聽從父母， 但現在的孩子不懂得服從
They are not because there is – they find that the parents among themselves
他們不，因為他們發現他們的父母
are not obedient to each other.
也對對方不順服
Also, they find the society is such, that where children go on
而且，他們發現這個社會上的孩子都
pestering the parents so they also become like that. But doesn’t matter,
令父母煩擾，所以他們也變得一樣，但這不重要
you are sahaja yogis, so you should bring up your children, who should be obedient,
你是一個霎哈嘉瑜伽士， 所以你要教育你的孩子，使他服從
who should be wise, who should be sensible,
他應該要聰明、應該要敏感
with the same love that the crocodile has for her little crocodiles.
如同那隻鱷魚對她的小鱷魚一般， 以同等的愛養育孩子
Now, when we come to the subtler side of Ganesha Tattwa,
現在，我們深入到伽涅沙原理的精微層面
that is, it expresses in our eyes.
就是，祂透過我們的眼睛表現出來
When I see some things,
當我看某個東西
I see it as a joy-giving thing, just joy-giving.
我將它看作能給予喜悅的東西，只是散發著喜悅
And if I want to buy something, then I think, “Alright,
如果我想要買某個東西，那我想：「好，
I can buy it for certain person. He will like it” -
我可以買給某個人，他會喜歡。」
because I’ll know what they like, so I’ll buy that thing for that person.”
因為我知道他們喜歡什麼，所以我會買這個給他
Or else if I’m buying something for my family, I think the same.
或者，如果我想買什麼給家人，我也會這樣想
Like I’ve built a house now where I’m going to put all the things,
就像我現在要建一個房子，我可以放所有
the presents you have given, everything, like a museum,
你們送我的禮物，就像一個博物館
and I’m going to ask all the villagers to come and see it.
接著，我要邀請那些村民來觀賞
Because they have never seen such things. They can’t travel to Switzerland,
因為他們從來沒有看過這些東西，他們不能到瑞士來旅行
leave alone England. So we have to –
更別說英國。所以我們必須要
I’m thinking of making that house in such a manner that these villagers,
我想著要建那個房子，所以那些
who have never seen beautiful things, should come and see.
從沒看過美麗物品的村民，可以來觀賞
In India, it’s not a case very much with the simple people to have jealousies.
在印度，通常純樸的人們不太會忌妒
Only the new materialistic people have developed this habit of jealousy.
只有新時代的物質主義，才發展出這樣忌妒的習慣
But otherwise, they will always say, “What a nice thing!
不然，他們總是會說：「多好的東西啊！
How beautiful it is! How they are!”
多麼美麗啊！多麼好！」
Like you were singing songs about Sahaja Yoga in Poona.
就像你們在浦那唱著霎哈嘉的歌
Actually, you have really picked up very well, I must say,
事實上，你們已經學得非常好了，我必須說
but there were masters of this music sitting there, watching you singing.
但那裡有音樂大師就坐在下面，看著你們演唱
They were the masters of drama and play, very well-known artists in India.
他們是戲劇的大師，在印度非常知名的藝術家
And then they said that…
之後他們說……
where you went to see their play, also in Poona if you remember.
如果你們記得，在浦那你們也看過他們的戲劇
So they offered Me, “Mother, that we want to celebrate Your birthday.”
他們跟我說：「母親，我們想要祝賀您的生日。」
I said, “It’s very difficult because you’ll be so far away.” “No, no, we’ll come!”
我說：「這對你們來說太遠了，太困難了。」 他們說：「不不，我們會來。」
The whole night they travelled
他們搭車搭了一天一夜
and the whole day, practically. They came about five o’clock, imagine.
他們到的時候是大約五點
They finished their drama about, say, 3 o’clock or 4 o’clock,
他們在大約三四點，結束他們的戲劇演出
and then they travelled all the day, arrived at about 5 o’clock
接著他們長途跋涉了一整天，大約在五點時抵達
from somewhere called Belgam, and 6:30 was the programme.
從貝爾高姆 (Belgaum)來，而節目演出的時間是六點半
So they were all dressed up, came, and what a comparing they did!
他們都著裝前來，看看他們說了什麼！
They said, “We were ashamed. We used to think that we Maharashtrians
他們說：「我們很慚愧，我們過去認為我們馬拉地人
are very good at music, very good at talas and this.
很懂音樂、很擅長塔拉(talas)，諸如此類
But we were ashamed the way these foreigners sang
但我們很慚愧，這些外國人唱
our music so well. We cannot sing like them.
我們的音樂如此出色，我們無法唱得像他們一樣
Though their music we cannot sing, while they sang our music
他們可以唱我們的音樂， 而我們卻無法唱他們的音樂
and we were all very much ashamed and embarrassed.
我們都感到很羞愧、很尷尬
How could they sing so well?” And the appreciation was so great
他們如何能唱得這麼好？」他們如此地讚美
that I was myself embarrassed, the way they were saying,
他們這樣講，我自己都覺得很不好意思
“How it has happened to these people? What is – their guru – have done?
這些人都是怎麼做到的？ 他們的導師做了什麼？
What have they done to these people, that they can sing so well?”
他們的導師做了什麼才讓他們可以唱得這麼好？
So the appreciation and the whole thing enamoured. We have a tape of that, I think.
他們如此傾心，給予這麼高的評價，我們有錄音帶
Audio tape; I don’t know if you have video tape or not,
音檔，我不知道你們是不是有影像檔
but if you have, please get it. It’s very interesting the way
如果你們有，一定要拿來看
they appreciated my children, the way they were singing.
他們如此稱讚我的孩子的歌唱，這非常有趣
And to them, I felt in their saying and all that,
而對於他們，我很喜歡他們的表現
because they are such masters and
因為他們是如此優秀的大師
so developed in their – the way they were appreciating,
非常精通音樂，但他們是如此的欣賞
as if they were appreciating children singing something great.
就像他們看到孩子們唱歌唱得很好
See the – in that the rapport was that of a – a very sweet rapport of vatsalya,
這是非常和諧的關係，非常甜美的Vatsalya般的關係
is the feeling of a motherliness,
意思是慈愛的感受
that, “Look at these children, are singing so well.”
看看這些孩子，他們唱得這麼好
It’s happened with many people I have seen, when some artists came, as you know,
這種特質存在在很多人身上， 當某些藝術家來，你知道的
that when they saw you people appreciating and singing, they had the same feeling,
當他們看到你們如此的欣賞並歌唱， 他們有一樣的感受
“How could these children – how could these people sing so well?
這些孩子，這些人是如何能唱得這麼好？
How did they know so well?”. I mean, all that beautiful feeling
他們如何有這麼多知識，所有那些美麗的感受
and all that appreciation created such a nice atmosphere,
所有的欣賞，創造了如此美好的環境
as we had some very great artists and how they appreciated you,
我們有些非常棒的藝術家，而他們是如此的欣賞你們
instead of saying that, “Oh, what, what are these,
而不是說：「噢這是什麼？
are no good for music and.” Nothing!
沒有任何音樂價值。」不是這樣！
They have so much appreciated that these people
他們如此地欣賞
who have never known Indian music are singing so well.
你們從未學過印度音樂，卻能唱得這麼好
So in that appreciation also, that fatherliness, that motherliness was there,
那樣的欣賞中，也有父愛、母愛在其中
that vatsalya was there, and the situation was so beautiful.
也有慈愛(Vatsalya)在那，那是非常美麗的
Even, say, when a person like Ravi Shankar has to play with Yehudi Menuhin.
甚至像拉維·香卡(Ravi Shankar)一樣大師級的人， 當他跟與耶胡迪·梅紐因(Yehudi Menuhin)一起演奏時
Yehudi Menuhin is a child before him. But I have seen how he looks after him
胡迪·梅紐因在他面前就像個孩子一樣。 但我也看到他是如何地照顧他
and how he protects him, as we say in my Hindi language “samhala”.
如何地保護他， 在印地語中我們稱作samhala
All the time is looking after him and managing it.
總是照顧著他
And also, we have seen in the music part, when supposing a tabla-wallah is sitting,
我們也看過在音樂上， 假設有一個塔布拉鼓手坐在這裡
and a very senior musician is sitting, Master is sitting.
還有一個非常資深的音樂家、大師坐在旁邊
He’ll say, “Please look after me, Samhala, look after me,”
他會說：「請多多關照，Samhala，請多關照。」
always with very great feeling of a child that, “You look after me.”
對一個孩子來說， 這是很深刻的感受：「你照顧著我。」
All these things are very important in life to create good relationships
在良好關係中，這都是非常重要的
between ourselves also. Those who are younger to us,
在瑜伽士之間也是，那些年紀比我們輕的
those who are not so well-off, or those who are not so much talented,
那些不是很富有的、那些不是很聰明的
or those who are not so much equipped in knowledge of Sahaja Yoga,
那些不是很了解霎哈嘉瑜伽知識的人
or who are not so much senior in Sahaja Yoga.
或在霎哈嘉瑜伽不是很資深
We have to look after the others, like in a very fatherly manner
我們要以一個父親的方式，照顧其他人
or, we can say, as a motherly manner, that they are not equipped. So alright.
或我們可以說，以一個母親的方式， 他們不是很有能力，沒關係
We have a Ganesha Tattwa, so excite their Ganesha Tattwa.
我們有伽涅沙原理，所以喚醒他們的伽涅沙原理
They should feel dependant on us for achieving the mastery,
他們應該要感到可以依賴我們，來熟悉霎哈嘉瑜伽
or achieving the higher state. As the Guru Principle
或達到更高的境界
If a guru does not have a Ganesh Principle,
如果一個導師沒有伽涅沙原理
he becomes a horrid, horrid, horrid fellow and nobody wants to stick onto him
他會成為一個可怕的傢伙， 沒有人想要跟他在一起
and they all run away from him. Though he might punish,
他們都會逃開他， 雖然導師可能會給予懲罰
he might also get angry with the disciples. But basically what he thinks,
他可能也會對門徒生氣，但基本上他是這樣想的：
“He is my progeny, I am developing him, I’m building up.”
「他是我的後代，我要開發、建立他！」
But in the modern thinking is that,
但現代的思考是
“Let them be individuals, let them be independent.”
「讓他們個體化、讓他們獨立」
So the father and mother do not look after their children in that manner
所以父親跟母親不再那樣地，照顧他們的孩子
that they should. “That see, this is my son, I’ve got a talent. I must teach him,
但他們應該這麼做。「看，這是我的兒子， 我有這樣的天賦，我應該要教他
he must come up, he is the one who is a continuation of my own self.”
他必須成長茁壯、他是我的延續。」
So this idea of having every individual, you are individual,
所以這種個體性的想法，你是一個個體
at eighteen years you get out of the house, you do what you like, stand on your legs.
十八歲之後你就離開家， 做任何你想做的事，靠自己獨立活著
No, life is a continuous basis. It is not just “you stand on your legs”,
不是這樣的，生命的本質是連續， 不只是「你獨立過活」
but is a question of one has to be all the time connected with the whole.
個體必須要無時無刻與整體連接
Unless and until you are connected completely,
除非你已經與整體完完全全地連結
we cannot understand collectivity of innocence.
我們無法理解純真的集體性
The collectivity of innocence, I see sometimes, I’m very happy
純真的集體性，我有看過幾次，我非常開心
that a child of somebody is in the lap of somebody, sitting very sweetly,
某個人的孩子在另一個人的腿上， 非常甜美地坐著
coming as if he is your own father, coming and sitting just on your lap,
就像他是你的父親一樣，走過來，坐在他的腿上
without knowing that, “He is not my father.”
不知道「他不是我的父親」
But still, that consciousness is not there.
他沒有那樣的意識
So this breaks the feeling of my and possession,
這能中斷「我的」和擁有的感覺
that, “This is mine, this is mine, this is mine.”
「這是我的、這是我的、這是我的」
And what makes you - the feeling that we are now a means,
現在我們是一種途徑
a means, we can say, an instrument,
一種途徑，或我們可以說一個工具
a media, by which we express the Ganesha Tattwa all over,
一個媒介，藉此彰顯伽涅沙原理
that is vibrations. So the vibrations itself, about which you are asking,
伽涅沙原理就是生命能量， 所以你在問的生命能量本身
these vibrations themselves are nothing but the Principle of Shri Ganesha.
生命能量本身不過就是錫呂．伽涅沙的原理
He is Omkara. And when it is, then what is it,
他是唵(Omkara)，而當祂是唵
that feeling as I told you, the vatsalya,
祂就成為，如同我告訴你的Vatsalya般的感受
the feeling of love between a child and a mother.
孩子與母親之間的那份愛
That feeling, it is the one that is vibrations,
那個感受，就是生命能量
between the child and the mother. The distance between the two is vibrations,
在孩子與母親之間的距離，就是生命能量
and that’s what one has to feel –
這就是你們必須去感受的
that he’s a child still and there’s the mother and mother is bringing the child,
他仍是一個孩子，母親養育孩子
giving all the powers to the child, bringing up, loving the child,
給這個孩子所有力量、將他帶大，愛這個孩子
understanding the limitations of the child, looking after, all that.
了解孩子的極限、照顧他，這所有一切
All the sweetness, all the wisdom of the child to be appreciated.
孩子所有的甜美行為，所有的智慧都應該被讚賞
That is vibrations. And if you see the subtle side of this,
那就是生命能量，如果你能看到這個的精微層面
it’s not “my” child. Should not – this is not only a limited thing,
那不是「我的」孩子，這不是這麼狹隘的事
because it is eternal, it’s everywhere, so you cannot have it limited.
因為生命能量是永恆的，是遍佈各地的， 所以祂不可能被限制
In everything you do, I have seen, people the way they handle things in the West –
在所有事情中都存在著生命能量， 我曾看過西方國家的人如何處理事情
we Indians have to learn also from them.
我們印度人也需要向他們學習
What’s happening?
怎麼了？
So we have to accept for them what is -
所以我們需要接受
what is the way to handle also beautiful things,
如何對待美麗的事物
how to look after beautiful things, how to manage beautiful relationships.
如何照顧美麗的事物、 如何經營美麗的人際關係
See, you shouldn’t be harsh, you shouldn’t be unkind, you shouldn’t say things,
你不應該嚴厲，你不應該刻薄， 你不應該說一些
which are insulting to others, so that the relationships are broken.
污辱別人的話，這樣關係就會破裂
So all the relationships that are between human beings and God,
所以，所有介於人類與神之間的關係
are through the Ganesha Principle. So when it becomes the relationship
都是透過伽涅沙原理，所以你與神的關係之間
between you and God, then there are vibrations.
存在著生命能量
And then that same relationship should extend to everything that you do.
接著，那樣的關係， 應該要被擴展到你做的所有事情之中
You should see what things are good, whatever has got vibrations.
你要判斷事物的好壞， 找出任何有生命能量的事物
Today I want to tell you something very important
今天我想告訴你一件很重要的事
about this all-pervading power we heard about.
關於我們聽過的，無所不在的上天能量
These are nothing but vibrations. This Paramachaitanya is nothing but vibrations,
這不過就是生命能量， 無所不在的上天能量(Paramachaitanya)就是生命能量
where all identities are lost –
而沒有了所有象徵性的身分
where the mother is lost, father is lost, we can say,
沒有母親、沒有父親
nothing remains, then it is just these vibrations, this subtle vatsalya exists.
沒有任何東西留下。 但只是純粹的生命能量， 只有這精微的母性的愛(vatsalya)存在著
That’s all. And this is the only thing,
只是這樣，這是唯一的事情
out of which everything comes and remains in itself.
這股生命能量創造萬物，而萬物之中亦存在著這股生命能量
Like we can say that the sun’s rays come out
像我們可以說
and then they try to create chlorophyll.
有了太陽光後，他們製造出葉綠素
So it’s not that we cannot compare sun with that.
但我們不能將太陽與葉綠素相提並論
Or we can say, from the ocean the clouds come out
或我們可以說，雲朵從海洋中生成
and they try to nourish the Mother Earth. That’s also not – cannot be compared.
接著他們試著滋養大地母親， 雲朵與海洋一樣不能被相提並論
Everything is inside that.
所有事物都在祂之中
This Paramachaitanya has got everything inside this.
無所不在的生命能量涵蓋著萬事萬物
So we can say that everything is nothing but knowledge,
所我們可以說，所有的事物不是別的、就是知識
is nothing but truth, is nothing but light.
不是別的，就是真相、就是光
But when the folds of these come out,
但當能量開始有起伏
then we get into the folds of that Chaitanya and then we become ignorant.
我們陷入生命能量的起伏之中，我們變得無知
But there is nothing like ignorance. It doesn’t exist, it doesn’t exist.
但無知不存在、無知並不存在
Like there is darkness because there’s no light.
就像黑暗存在，是因為沒有光
Once light comes, it doesn’t exist, doesn’t exist. So ignorance doesn’t exist.
一旦有光亮，黑暗便不存在，所以無知並不存在
But what happens that the folds of this ocean, into that people go and it is lost.
所以，人們迷失在這能量海洋的波浪之中
Thus we understand one thing very clearly:
因此我們清楚地明白一件事
that we are in Paramachaitanya. We are made by Paramachaitanya,
我們在生命能量之中， 我們是生命能量所創造的
all the time we are surrounded by it. Only thing is,
無時無刻我們都被祂所圍繞
we are sometimes lost in the folds.
只是我們有時會迷失在波浪之中
And why? Why we are lost in the folds
為什麼？為什麼我們會迷失在波浪之中？
is because of our own – our own unawareness.
因為我們自己沒有意識到
This awareness has to come: that we are part and parcel of that Paramachaitanya.
我們必須要意識到， 我們是無所不在的生命能量的一部份
The whole thing is called as chidvilasa, is the vilas,
這被稱為chidvilasa、是vlasa
is the playful enjoyment of God’s Attention.
是神的注意力所作的遊戲般的享受
Now you will say, “How can that be?”
現在你可能會說：「怎麼可能是那樣？」
For example, we see the sun –just to give a simile closer to it,
舉例來說，我們看太陽，只是藉此做個比喻
we see the sun and then we see the water. We see the water in the lake, alright?
我們看太陽，我們再看水， 我們看湖中的水，好嗎？
There is water – because of the sun, we can see the water there.
那裡有水，是因為太陽，我們才能看到那裡有水
Then supposing, we see the mirage.
接著，假設我們看到了海市蜃樓
We see the mirage and then we think this is water,
我們看到海市蜃樓，然後我們以為這是水
we go run after the water. But the whole thing is the play of the sun:
我們追逐著那個水，但這整件事情都是太陽的遊戲
whether it’s a mirage, whether it’s a water, whether it’s the sun.
無論這是海市蜃樓、或是水、或是太陽
In the same way, this Paramachaitanya acts
這無所不在的生命能量，也是同樣的方式在作用
and what we get lost is, in our awareness, that we are Paramachaitanya.
而我們迷失在其中， 在我們的意識之中， 我們以為我們就是生命能量
That’s why the play starts, the play starts
這就是戲劇開始的原因
like yesterday’s – day before yesterday’s Puja, what did we do?
戲劇開始演出就像前天的普祭，我們做了什麼？
We were sitting there and it started raining.
我們坐在那裡，接著開始下雨
So - to prove, to prove that I can control rain.
所以那是為了證明，證明我能控制雨
So it rained. Some people were covering up, some thing, this thing.
所以開始下雨，有些人開始拿東西遮
I gave a bandhan. After some time, the rain moved out
我給了一個班丹。過了一段時間
from the Puja to the back side. It was not raining where you were sitting.
雲朵開始從普祭處移到後面， 你們坐著的地方沒有在下雨了
And after that, it became a sun and it was so clouded.
之後太陽出來了， 但之前是那麼的烏雲密布
Sun came, it was, became sunny,
太陽出來了，變成晴天
so that’s how you have to become aware of the powers of Chaitanya.
所以你必須意識到生命能量的力量
Now when you give bandhan, what you do is to put the Chaitanya into action,
所以當你給班丹，你做了甚麼， 你使生命能量作出行動
“Now act here, act there, act here.”
「現在在這裡作用，在那裡、在這裡。」
Though you are, supposing, in the ocean, but the ocean acts on you all the time.
即便你在能量的海洋裡， 能量無時無刻都在你身上作用
You cannot act on the ocean, you cannot ask water
你不能作用在海洋之上，你不能叫海水
to do this and do that. But as realised souls, you are empowered,
做這個做那個。 但當你是自覺的靈，你被賦予權力
now you can ask water, “Alright, you dissolve this, you do this, you do that.”
現在你可以叫海水， 你溶解這個、你做這個、你做那個
But for that, it is important to be the masters.
但要達到那樣，成為導師是非常重要的
And to become the masters, you see - like a matter becomes a human being,
要成為導師，你看， 就像物質變成人類
and from human being, you have to become the masters of the matter
而從人類，你必須要能夠支配物質的導師
and you handle the matter.  So we come back to the same.
而你掌控物質，所以我們要回到同一個點
Like agriculture, we can handle, just vibrating it.
就像農業，我們可以掌控它，只要給它生命能量
We can handle water, we can handle the sun,
我們可以掌控水，我們可以掌控太陽
we can handle moon - because there’s a rapport.
我們可以掌控月亮，因為這是一個和諧融洽的關係
Now we are aware, a rapport has been established.
現在我們有此意識，和諧的關係就被建立了
So all this play is extremely beautiful to me. I see it.
所以所有的戲劇，在我看來都是非常美麗的
But now you all have to know that you all have become realised souls
但現在你們都要知道， 你們都已經獲得自覺
and you have those powers. So all other nonsensical things that you learn,
而且你擁有這些力量， 所以你所學的那些荒謬的事情
all nonsensical things you indulge into, you’d better give up.
你沉溺的那些荒謬的東西，你最好放棄
There’s no sense in it. Whatever is sensible you should do
那完全沒有意義，你應該要做明智的事情
because there’s Shri Ganesha within you, who is absolutely sensible.
因為錫呂．伽涅沙在你之內， 而祂是非常明智的
He is nothing but sense. He is the giver of sense,
祂就是明智本身，祂是明智的給予者
so He is the killer of the demons, as they say.
所以他們說祂是惡魔的毀滅者
He is the one who removes all the ordeals. By how?
祂是移除所有苦難者，怎麼做到的？
By improving our awareness.
藉由提升我們的意識形態
Though ordeals do not remain because you give a bandhan, it works out.
儘管有磨難也不會持續， 因為你給了班丹，祂會起作用
Now I asked somebody – Phil – I asked him to write down about the miracles,
現在我要求某個人Phil， 我要求他寫下這些奇蹟
and he says now it has become like a voluminous book.
他說現在已經累積成了一本卷帙浩繁的書了
It will be because before realization
會這樣的，因為在得到自覺前
whatever looked like miracle is no more a miracle. Miracle has lost its meaning.
無論看起來是如何奇蹟的事都不再是奇蹟了， 奇蹟已經失去了它的意義
Because now you are empowered and you can do it.
因為現在你已經被授權了，而且你可以做到
It works in everything: in your talent, in your understanding,
這作用於方方面面， 在你的天賦上、你的理解力
in your education, in every way. Like there are some boys who said,
你的教育，方方面面，就像有些男孩他們說
“Mother, You see, we couldn’t solve one problem so we gave a bandhan.
「母親，你看，我們不能解決問題， 所以我們給了班丹
Immediately the whole thing came onto us and we wrote it down” and they stood first.
解決方案馬上降臨到我們身上，我們把它寫下來。」 接著他們駐足那裡
It has happened with many. So in every action, in everything,
這發生過很多次，所以每一個動作、每一件事情
whatever you do, you should know it is the Paramachaitanya that acts.
無論你做什麼， 你應該要知道這是生命能量在作用
Only thing you have to be aware of yourself, and aware of it, it acts;
你必須要意識到你自己 和意識到這股能量，祂在作用
and you just jump into that awareness and it works.
你只要躍升至這意識，祂會成就
And that you have seen. But still, so many people do not know.
你們已經見過了，但還是很多人不知道
So many people still, though they know through their brains,
有很多人還是認為他們是透過他們的大腦認知事物
do not know in their hearts. And so many people,
不認識他們的心，而很多人
even if they know in their hearts, they do not act in their attention.
即使他們認識他們的心， 他們不會顯示在他們的注意力上
So only these three things you have to improve: is one is your head,
所以只有這三件事你們需要提升，一個是你的頭
another is your heart and third is your liver.
另一個是你的心、第三個是你的肝臟
If you can improve these three organs, this Paramachaitanya will act.
如果你可以改善這三個器官， 這個生命能量就能行動
But then, all this attention about money.
但所有的注意力依舊在金錢上
So many people, money this, that. There’s nothing to worry.
那麼多人，金錢這個那個， 那沒有什麼好擔心的
Paramachaitanya will create everything for you, whatever you want.
生命能量會創造所有事物給你，無論你想要什麼
It may not create money because it doesn’t have a mint, but it will create
祂不會創造金錢，因為祂沒有一個鑄幣廠， 但祂會創造
possibilities –
可能性
possibilities. And this is something to be understood very well, and it’s so blissful
可能性。而這必須要被好好了解， 這是非常受祝福的
to know that now you are aware of the Paramachaitanya
可以得知， 現在你們意識到無所不在的生命能量
and you can master it. Master it in the sense not that you dominate it,
而且你可以精通祂， 精通祂而不是支配祂
but you ask him like a jinn. You know, you can say,
但你可以像個神燈精靈一樣的要求祂， 你知道，你可以說
“All right, do this, do that”, with respect. With respect it works.
「好，做這個、做那個」尊敬地說。 尊敬就會起作用
But the way sometimes we do not pay respect to Paramachaitanya
但有時候我們也並不尊敬生命能量
is also something surprising. The way we act all the time, the way we are behaving.
這非常令人驚訝， 我們總是以這種方式行動、待人處事
Like in my presence, people will sit down and close their eyes,
像是在我在場時， 大家會坐下，閉上他們的眼睛
or they will start worshipping the photograph instead of me.
或是，他們會開始對照片做崇拜，而不是對我
Sometimes, the way they handle their Kundalini,
有時是，他們對待他們的昆達里尼的方式
sometimes, the way they behave towards themselves and others -
有時是，他們對待他們自己和對待他人的方式
all these things are to be understood,
你們都要知道這些事情
now that we have entered into the Kingdom of God,
現在我們已經進入了神的國度
means Paramachaitanya, and that we are very important citizens of that.
也就是無所不在的生命能量。 而且我們是其中非常重要的人民
If one can understand this, then I think, Sahaja Yoga can be very successful.
如果你們可以瞭解到這一點， 那我想，霎哈嘉瑜伽可以非常成功
Everything will work out. It, miraculously, everything will work out.
所有事情都會成就。 奇蹟似的，所有事情都會成就
And all those who are not aware
所有那些沒有意識到
about the possibilities as to what they can reach,
他們有多大可能性的人
they are thrown out, in the sense, in the fold,
他們會被拋出去， 也就是他們會陷入表面的波浪中
in the ignorance, so-called, into the darkness.
陷入無知、陷入黑暗之中
Again they can come back to light when they have sense.
如果他們有智慧， 他們可以再次回到光亮之中
So be forgiving about them. It can happen to you also
所以要原諒他們， 這也有可能會發生在你們身上
if you understand that way.
如果你明白其原因
I hope, today’s lecture you have been able to assimilate within yourself.
我希望今天的演講能被你們理解、內化
That’s very important to assimilate, to know that you are in the Paramachaitanya.
內化是非常重要的，知道你就是生命能量
And that’s how you’ll become very sweet, you’ll become very considerate,
藉此，你變得非常甜美、你變得非常體貼
and very loving, affectionate and wise. That’s very important.
非常有愛，充滿感情並且有智慧，那是非常重要的
May God bless you.
願神祝福你
The point, about which some leaders have said, that
有些領導者曾說過
you people don’t buy individually my tapes.
你們自己本身不買我的錄影帶
And then, you come to the ashrams and want to listen to my tapes again and again.
之後你到靈舍來，想要一而再再而三地聽我的演講
And you spoil the tapes. This is wrong.
接著你損害了那個錄影帶，這是錯誤的
You are all sahaja yogis, you must respect.
你們都是霎哈嘉瑜伽士，你必須尊重
And all of you must try to get the tapes properly,
你們所有人都要試著適當地取得錄影帶
in proper manner, and should use your own tapes carefully and with respect.
以適當的方法，應該要小心地、 帶著尊敬地使用你們自己的錄影帶
Because some people are taking away also the tapes from the ashrams and using them.
因為有些人甚至拿走靈舍的錄影帶，去使用
No, it’s very precious. All of you should treat it as a very precious thing.
不是這樣，這是非常珍貴的。 所有人都應該看將它視為一個非常珍貴的物品
And all of you should take tapes which have been created by the ashram and use them.
你們所有人都應該要取得靈舍所製作的錄影帶，並使用他們
But in the ashram you can use it once in a while.
但在靈舍你可以偶爾使用一兩次
But for your house, for your car -
但在你的家裡，在你的車上
or I have seen that in other horrible false guru’s people, they just take
或我甚至看過其他可怕的假導師，他們就拿錄影帶
the tapes, never play any music, nothing, they are just playing the tapes.
不播音樂，什麼都沒有，他們就只是撥放錄影帶
So in the same way, you can have that,
所以同樣的，你可以有錄影帶
because it’s not easy to understand my lecture in one first shot.
因為我的演講不容易聽一次就理解
You have to individually sit down and listen to it
你必須要單獨坐下來聆聽
and decode it and see for yourself, what it is.
你自己要解讀它、並理解它，那是什麼
Because my - I myself when I listen to my lectures, I get lost.
因為我… 聽我自己的演講，我也迷失了